Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
What a stupid fool!
She didn't tell me she was feeling unwell!
Concubine Sourire said she was ill several times.
Your Highness didn't believe her ...
How would I know if she was faking it?
She's always been a smooth talker, and always defying me.
Why would she ...
She had just entered her fourth month of pregnancy.
Her pregnancy should have been stable.
Why did she bleed after kneeling for just an hour?
The imperial doctor said ...
Blood ...
The blood ...
I was bleeding when I had my miscarriage too.
Your Highness,
even if a doctor said kneeling for an hour is fine,
you can't really make her kneel for that long.
There's always a chance ...
Why didn't you say so?
Now your hindsight is twenty-twenty!
Your Highness!
Your Highness, for the good of your health, please don't be angry.
Your Highness,
the procession of His Majesty and Her Majesty
has arrived at the Xuanwu Gate.
[north gate of the palace]
So quickly.
Any news from the Palace of Pearl Jade?
Did she keep her child?
All the doctors are still gathered there
but no news has come out.
Lady Cao, Noble Lady Cao,
Her Highness did not mean you any harm.
Her Highness is frightened and angry.
You must think of a way to help Her Highness.
Your Highness, whether Concubine Sourire
had a miscarriage or not,
His Majesty's immediate return shows
he has been informed of the incident.
For Your Highness to protect yourself,
you might have to humble yourself to avoid angering His Majesty.
Why?
I did nothing wrong.
That's not what matters right now.
What matters is what His Majesty thinks.
An apology doesn't mean Your Highness admits any fault.
But acting humbly will quell His Majesty's anger.
I did nothing wrong.
His Majesty will ascertain the truth when he arrives.
Yes, His Majesty will.
But when he sees Concubine Sourire ...
His Majesty will only investigate
how she was reduced to her condition.
No matter Concubine Sourire lost her child or not,
His Majesty will be in fierce anger.
If Your Highness cares about His Majesty's favor in the future,
you have to hold your head down for now.
Your Majesty... Your Majesty.
Your Majesty...
Why is Concubine Sourire still unconscious?
Her Highness's sudden miscarriage greatly damaged her health.
She also has heatstroke symptoms from
kneeling in the blazing sun at midday.
We have to keep giving her medicine to help her revive.
I'll do it.
Hold her up.
Does His Majesty know that My Lady was saved by Lord XVII?
He does.
Did His Majesty say something?
His Majesty hurried back upon hearing the news.
Where is Lord XVII?
The Empress Dowager is unwell.
Lord XVII is taking care of her in the Hall of Converging Light.
I'll return inside then.
His Majesty will make a fair decision.
You don’t have to stare at me here.
Meizhaung,
don’t argue with her now.
Let’s see Sourire first.
Let’s go.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesty.
HuanHuan.
Are you awake?
It is a blessing from Heaven you’re finally awake.
You’ve been sleeping for hours.
Your Majesty.
You have returned.
HuanHuan.
I am deeply sorry.
Your Majesty.
My child ... Is my child all right?
We will have another child someday.
My Lady.
Your Majesty ...
My child ...
Your Majesty!
My child!
My Lady.
Please don’t cry Sourire.
If you are grieved, His Majesty will feel even deeper grief.
The imperial carriages returned in haste upon hearing the news.
Your Majesty.
This is no time for mourning.
Concubine Sourire has lost her child
through man-made, not natural causes.
Where is that shrew?
Your Majesty,
Noble Consort Fleur has unfastened her hair and awaits judgment.
She is kneeling outside the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Bring her in.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Your Highness, His Majesty wants to see you.
Has Concubine Sourire’s child been saved?
Be careful, Your Highness!
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
I am guilty.
Concubine Sourire offended me today,
and I only intended to impose a modest punishment as a warning.
I didn't mean for her to miscarry.
I don't understand how this happened.
I hope Your Majesty
will pardon my ignorant offense.
Were you ignorant?
Did you not know that Concubine Sourire
was three months pregnant?
- Your Majesty!
- Your Majesty,
Her Imperial Highness insisted that
Concubine Souire's pregnancy was stable
and that was the reason she could kneel for so long.
Your Majesty, I didn't know!
I completely lost my head today.
I thought it would be fine for her to kneel for an hour.
What kind of doctor are you?
How could she have a miscarriage after kneeling for just an hour?
What tonic did you give her and now
you're trying to blame it on me?
Her Highness has been feeling unwell recently
but that is normal for expectant mothers during the hot summer.
But there is another factor.
Her Highness has been experiencing anxiety recently,
which caused instability in her pregnancy.
But that wouldn't have been an issue if Her Highness had continued resting.
Your Majesty, I heard your Lord Consort had a
miscarriage after kneeling for four hours.
That's why...
That's why I thought it would be fine for
Concubine Sourire to kneel for only an hour.
The Lord Consort was punished that day
for her major disrespect to Empress Première.
Besides, Empress Première was entirely unaware
that my Lord Consort was pregnant.
It was an honest mistake.
Empress Première had a kind heart.
She was consumed with guilt for her mistake,
and that caused her to experience
difficult labor and excessive bleeding.
But you!
You clearly knew Concubine Sourire was
pregnant and forcibly punished her.
And now you don't even show any remorse for your actions.
Vile wretch!
How dare you compare yourself to Empress Première!
I was ignorant.
You were not ignorant.
You were intentionally cruel!
If Concubine Sourire really committed an offense,
why didn't you punish her early in the morning?
Why did you have to wait until noon
to make her kneel in the scorching midday heat?
What a vicious heart "like the snakes and scorpions"!
How can I allow your presence in my palace?
Your Majesty! Your Majesty!
It's true that I don't like Concubine Sourire.
Ever since she entered the palace,
Your Majesty stopped favoring me as before.
Concubine Sourire grew conceited over her favor and insulted me.
How could I possibly tolerate it?
You're such a fool!
His Majesty trusted you to manage palace affairs.
Look how you have abused that trust!
I've been displeased with Concubine Sourire's arrogant attitude.
But I never harbored any intention to harm her child.
I have the experience of losing my own child.
How could I be so heartless to others?
"If you don't want it to be done to you, don't do it to others."
You have experienced the pain of losing a child.
How could you inflict the same
upon Concubine Sourire?
Even if you didn't intend to harm her child,
her child was lost because of you.
You can't escape the responsibility.
I can no longer tolerate "a person with the heart of a snake and scorpion".
The Empress will announce to the palace
that Imperial Consort of the Nian Family
is demoted to the rank of Consort,
and deprived of her honorary name
and the power to assist in palace affairs.
She will not be seen unless summoned.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Shall I inform Her Majesty as well?
Her Majesty has been very sad about Lady Fuca's miscarriage.
Now that she is unwell,
this would be "adding hail to the snow".
So don't mention it to her.
I'll be careful that Her Majesty will not be disturbed.
Your Majesty need not worry.
Your Majesty,
It was my unwitting mistake.
Will Your Majesty have mercy?
But what was Concubine Sourire's mistake?
And what was the mistake of all the concubines?
They all had to endure the scorching sun with Concubine Sourire!
From now on,
every midday,
you will kneel at the gate of your palace for four hours.
Get out!
Your Highness,
Mr. Su,
His Majesty has never been so angry at me before.
What shall I do?
Please go, Your Highness.
Pardon me for saying this,
no matter how much Your Highness dislikes Concubine Sourire,
you should not be that impulsive.
I'm wrongfully convicted.
Only if His Majesty is willing to trust you.
Take care, Your Highness.
You may all leave. I will stay with Concubine Sourire.
Yes.
Concubine Sourire, your health is the most important.
You have ample years ahead of you.
Be measured in your grief.
Today,
if Lord XVII had not rescued you from the Palace of Earthly Honor
and sent someone to inform me,
it's hard to imagine how much worse it might have turned out.
How much worse ...
can it turn out?
Don't be so sad.
You are young.
We'll easily have another child after your recovery.
Your Majesty,
I venture to ask you,
Did my child just die for nothing?
Why didn't you enact your wrath by killing that wretch?
We are in pressing need for support in court.
I had to take that into account.
But she has killed Your Majesty's child.
It's all my fault.
But today ...
Why did you have to be so obedient to Consort Nian?
You didn't have to kneel or submit to her punishment.
Consort Estime was there.
Why didn't you seek help from her?
Your Majesty knows what kind of person Nian is.
How could Consort Estime stop her?
How could I possibly confront her?
Under the circumstances,
had I disobeyed her orders,
she would have had more excuses to
impose punishments on me.
Why did Your Majesty ...
why did you give her absolute power in palace affairs?
Your Majesty was not unaware of her cruelty.
You knew how she caused Meizhuang's
wrongful demotion and suffering.
Are you blaming me?
How dare I?
Huan Huan.
I swear to Heaven
that I will bring you justice.
I request Your Majesty to tell me when.
One day.
The pain of losing a child might fade over time.
But Consort Nian will continue to be in the palace.
How am I going to live my days like before?
And Your Majesty ...
you might become sentimental about the past.
Huan Huan.
Please try to endure this for a little longer.
Please do it for me.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
You may leave now.
Yes.
You must have waited for a while.
I wanted to attend the Palace of Pearl Jade when I returned with His Majesty,
but the Empress Dowager summoned me.
You've been worried all night. Ask me.
Did Concubine Sourire ...
Her child wasn't saved.
It was my incompetence.
I was carried away by the competition for fame at the infirmary.
I didn't protect My Lady.
Why are you standing here crying?
You're a man!
She was harmed intentionally.
What could a doctor have done?
I wish I could be more useful.
It's not a good time for you to attend at the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Huan'er will be sad when she sees you
and you didn't undertake any duty for her pregnancy.
It's not appropriate for you to go.
If you have the intention to help her,
you can carefully examine her recent
prescriptions and leftover herbs.
See if there's anything wrong.
I have my concerns about this.
Consort Nian was overbearing
but she wouldn't dare to so blatantly harm an imperial heir.
I will commit this to my care, My Lady.
Don't inform the Zhen family yet.
Her parents would be overwhelmed by grief.
That's very thoughtful of you, My Lady.
I understand.
Your Majesty.
Are those just routine greetings?
Yes.
Leave them there.
What's wrong?
Your Majesty,
this one is from Great General Nian.
He already sent one in yesterday.
Now there's another.
How many more greetings does he have?
Shifu, your clothes are soaking wet.
You should go get changed.
Since Concubine Sourire lost her child,
His Majesty hasn't slept well - for two days now.
The situation has caused severe “internal fire."
Don't walk around unnecessarily, understand?
What a day!
It's almost midday.
Consort Nian must be kneeling at her gate.
Go away.
Your Highness,
you have been kneeling here for three days.
You had sunstroke yesterday.
Your Highness must care for your health.
If I don't kneel here,
His Majesty will still be angry.
If His Majesty is angry,
he will not forgive me.
Go.
I said go!
Your Highness!
Your Highness! Are you all right?
Help!
Your Majesty, Lord XVII is here to pay his respects.
Send him in.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty,
I am here to seek your punishment.
You may rise.
Have a seat.
What’s the matter?
When I heard about what was happening
at the Palace of Earthly Honor,
I had no better choice than entering Your Majesty's harem.
I deserve Your Majesty’s punishment.
You've said that was the only possible choice.
How can I blame you?
It's known to all that Your Majesty cherishes Consort Sourire.
And Lady Fuca's miscarriage was so recent.
I couldn't bear to see the loss of another child of Your Majesty's.
You did all you could.
It is Heaven that disapproves.
We can do nothing about that.
Your Majesty should have more rest.
Your countenance has been disturbed
by events in the harem.
Reviewing the memorandums now is not good for your health.
This is the greeting from Nian Gengyao.
Have a look.
General Nian cares more about
Your
Majesty’s family affairs than state affairs.
Since he is my family,
he can ask about my family affairs within bounds of propriety.
But as a courtier,
he is throwing his weight around,
holding me in contempt.
Your Majesty and General Nian are monarch and
subject before relatives through marriage.
It’s a pity that he doesn’t understand.
While Consort Nian is punished,
Nian Gengyao sends his greetings to her in every message.
His meaning is clear.
If he behaves like this to Your Majesty, that is
disrespectful to his master and monarch.
If he behaves like this to the people,
he is abusing Your Majesty's trust and favor.
You rarely pass comment on state affairs.
I am ... your brother.
I only talk about family affairs.
Your Majesty, the Palace of Earthly Honor reports
that Consort Nian fainted from heatstroke.
Did the doctors visit?
They are in attendance.
Tell Consort Nian that she is exempt from
her daily kneeling until she recovers.
Aye.
Your Majesty is caring.
You feel sentimental about the past despite her grave mistake.
Nian Shilan has been very conscientious over the years.
I don't want to destroy her spirit from overly stern punishment.
She and her brother are very caring for one another.
Dispiriting one would dishearten the other.
Nian Gengyao has made that very clear.
"I am deeply disturbed by Consort Nian's demotion."
"As if my heart was in the chill of the winter
and my five viscera in the haze of a fog."
He is disappointed and devastated.
He's not thinking through what he says and does.
Consort Nian harmed an imperial heir
and her offense is unpardonable.
It’s like “pulling a single hair affects the whole body”.
A lenient punishment on her won't restore discipline in the harem
and assuage Concubine Sourire's grief.
But a severe punishment ...
She has been in favor all these years ...
Even if ...
Even if I wasn't sentimental about the past,
I have to take the many powers in the court into account.
What would you do if you were me?
“Those who are not in office should not
concern themselves with the job.” [Confucius]
I’m an indecisive and incapable person when it comes to serious matters.
I would be distressed seeing the tears of beautiful women.
Combined with state affairs, it will "turn my head into wheat paste".
You've always shirked your duties at the court.
But now I can't allow you to keep doing that.
With some things, you must lend me a hand.
I am a witless man, but there's one thing I understand —
Do what Your Majesty says.
I will obey Your Majesty's orders.
Your Highness. Your Highness.
- Your Highness is awake.
- Your Majesty.
Did His Majesty come?
Your Highness had a heatstroke.
The imperial doctor advised Your Highness
not to exert yourself again.
Your Highness should lie down.
Has His Majesty been informed that I fainted from a heatstroke?
I have sent quite a few groups of servants
to report to His Majesty ...
But ...
Your Highness.
You woke up, My Lady.
My Lady, you are still recovering.
Sitting like this might cause you back pain.
No matter how much pain I have now,
I feel like I deserve it.
I have been regretting every day ...
Why didn't I beg for Consort Nian's forgiveness that day?
Why was I so stubborn, not bowing down my head?
If only I had begged,
I might have been able to save my child.
It's not your fault, My Lady.
Even if you were willing to give in,
Consort Nian still would not have let you off easily.
Why did I want to gain His Majesty's favor?
If I had lived in obscurity,
Consort Nian wouldn’t have been jealously resenting me,
fighting me with such deadly force.
My hate won't subside even if she receives
"death by a thousand cuts".
But what about me?
I'm the one who made the stupidest mistake.
My Lady,
please don’t continue blaming yourself.
You can only look forward. There's no turning back.
You could never have foreseen that day's misfortune.
You are not at fault.
This bib ...
I was so happy making it for my baby.
The bib is still here,
but my child
will never enter this world.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
How's Concubine Sourire?
My Lady didn’t sleep well last night.
She’s having a nap.
You don’t need to announce my arrival.
I’ll go in myself.
It’s no good if you keep crying like this, My Lady.
If you keep crying so much,
you might have watery eyes when exposed to the wind in the future.
The older servants in the palace said that
the Empress Dowager's chronic illness
developed for the same reason.
Her Majesty is deeply blessed.
I can’t compare with her.
If His Majesty sees you like this, My Lady,
it will bring so many painful memories to you both.
If His Majesty stops visiting the
Palace of Pearl Jade because of that,
it’s no good for you, My Lady.
Ten days haven't even passed since I lost my child.
How could I, as a mother, forget my grief, and dress myself up to please others?
You needn't please anyone, My Lady.
You are in your prime age.
You can conceive babies in the future as long as you have His Majesty's favor.
You shouldn't give in to grief like this, my lady.
I don't mean to.
But once I see His Majesty,
I can't help but think of my child.
I can't even force a smile.
You were absent-minded at the dinner table.
Recently, you seem to be exhausted.
I am worried about you.
I'm all right.
The doctor has prepared some medicine to lessen the internal heat.
Su Peisheng will serve it to you later.
Go to bed early.
Imperial doctors' medicines are always bitter.
They will only add more bitterness to my heart.
I apologize for my bad mood, Imperial Mother.
I know you are deeply upset,
as Lady Fuca and Concubine Sourire both lost their children.
These days, you hardly come to the harem.
Imperial Mother,
There is always a doubt in my mind.
Even though Consort Nian is overbearing, and she dislikes Concubine Sourire,
it still doesn't make any sense that Concubine Sourire lost her child
after she knelt down for only one hour in the Palace of Earthly Honor.
I have the same doubt.
And I have ordered them to investigate it.
Once Consort Nian held power, she emphasized
her status over the other concubines.
Every day, she summoned the concubines to her palace.
They were seldom allowed to leave until
staying there for six to eight hours.
Concubine Sourire had disliked Consort Nian for long.
Inevitaby her strong emotions would have damaged her health.
It wouldn't cause such a serious result.
The Palace of Earthly Honor has long been burning ...
Mother, you don't need to say more.
It's all my fault.
It's not. You prioritize national interests over all else.
You did nothing wrong.
Also, in my opinion,
the daily consumption of the incense is small
and it is only effective after being used for a long time.
That's why you and I were never concerned
over concubines visiting the Palace of Earthly Honor.
As for Concubine Sourire,
she was never in the Palace of
Earthly Honor except in those few days.
Think carefully.
Can there be other reasons besides this?
When I began to favor Concubine Sourire,
Escort Yu put poison into her medicine.
The poisoning went on for quite a few days before being discovered.
That's the reason.
Concubine Sourire had previously been poisoned.
Possibly, her physical state was too weakened to prevent the miscarriage.
In this case, you should not blame yourself anymore.
Your Majesty, Doctor Zhang has been waiting for you for a long time.
Call him here.
Yes.
The culpable official Zhang Mi bows before Your Majesty.
It's late for you to ask to see me. Is there
anything wrong with Concubine Sourire?
Concubine Sourire is well.
I am here to ask for Your Majesty's forgiveness.
I am over sixty years.
I was too old to follow Your Majesty's order to protect Concubine Sourire's child.
I failed to accomplish my duty.
You did your utmost to serve Concubine Sourire.
This time, it's not your fault.
Concubine Sourire lost her child.
I am deeply saddened by the loss of an imperial heir.
I haven't been able to eat, or sleep well.
I no longer deserve to serve as an imperial doctor.
You are an experienced doctor
and you have long served in the harem.
That's why I feel so guilty.
As a doctor, failing to prevent the loss of life
will be the regret of all my life.
I'm incapable of fulfilling my duties.
Now, the Imperial Infirmary is full of professional and talented doctors.
So, I intend to retire from my position and return to my hometown.
If you insist on it,
I can't bend you to my will.
I allow you to retire and return to your hometown.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.